James A. Paddock Additional Papers 5833
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
James A. Paddock Additional Papers
1954-1988
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Paddock, James A.
5833
3 cubic feet
3 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
This collection consists of the papers of James A. Paddock, former president of the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen, documenting the industry-wide effort to curb drug and alcohol abuse in railroad operating employees.
5713660
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, July 10, 2017
EAD encoding:
E. Parker, July 10, 2017
Biographical / Historical
James A. Paddock spent his entire life working in the railroad industry. After completing his education at the University of San Francisco in 1937, he entered train service as a brakeman and switchman for the Bingham and Garfield Railway, part of the Kennecott Utah Copper rail line in Salt Lake County, Utah. He was promoted to conductor in 1941. Starting in 1938, Mr. Paddock became active with the Order of Railway Conductors [ORC] as a General Committee Member. In 1948, he accepted full-time employment as Assistant to the President of the International Union, headquartered in Cedar Rapids, Iowa. In 1954, he was elected to the office of Senior Vice-President, and in 1958 to the Office of President. During his tenure as president of ORC, he served on the Presidential Railroad Commission from 1959-1961. In 1961, Mr. Paddock retired from the ORC presidency in order to seek treatment for his alcoholism.
In 1963, Mr. Paddock returned to work in the railroad industry, joining the Association of Western Railways as a Special Representative to the Law Department, working on matters where labor and management had a mutual interest, such as safety on grade crossings. He retired from active railroad employment in 1970 because of a health issue.
In 1971, Mr. Paddock began training as a counselor specializing in alcohol and drug addiction. With his new training, Mr. Paddock began to work as an independent consultant in the area of industrial programs and other aspects involving alcohol and drug related research and development in the work place. In this capacity, he assisted the Milwaukee Road, the Illinois Central, and the Elgin, Joliet and Eastern Railway in setting up Employee Assistance Programs [EAP] and other services designed to improve safety and operations. In 1973, he began consulting for the Federal Railroad Administration in this capacity. He took part in two major studies of alcoholism and drug abuse in the railroad industry in 1976 and 1979, conducting research and writing the reports. The 1979 report became known as the REAP report. He continued his work in this area with officers of the United Transportation Union [UTU], specifically Daniel Collins, in the 1980s. Using the EAP of the Union Pacific as their model, the UTU championed a labor- management supported program called Operation Red Block designed to help railroad operating employees with substance abuse problems and to help their co-workers know how to appropriately respond and help their fellows. A key component of these programs are the so-called "Rule G By-Pass Agreements." Rule G is the prohibition against operating while intoxicated. The By-Pass Agreements allow for voluntary self-reporting or co-worker reporting on a one time basis so that an employee might avoid serious disciplinary measures for the first offense and be put into a counseling program to address their addiction.
Mr. Paddock, in a speech he gave in 1983, called this work his avocation.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1954-1988
Bulk dates: 1975-1988
This collection consists of the papers of James A. Paddock. The majority of the papers document his work in the 1970s and 1980s combatting drug and alcohol abuse in the railroad industry. This collection also contains some records of the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen [ORC] and the report of the Presidential Commission on Railroads.
Of note in this collection are the records documenting the ways in which the railroad industry, both labor and management, attempted to address problems of substance abuse among its employees, in particular among its operating employees. The programs include various EAPs, including Operation: Red Block. Records documenting industry research, substance abuse research, employee training, and counselor training are found in this collection. Also found are the records of various Senate and House bills, hearings, and committees which attempt to address substance abuse issues through federal statutes and operating guidelines. The lawsuits filed by the Railway Labor Executives' Association [RLEA] in opposition to some of these proposed guidelines, such as random drug testing, on constitutional grounds. The clippings files give a broad overview of the national mood at the time, and demonstrate how some of these programs intersected with President Reagan's War on Drugs, and the disastrous consequences it had.
Of note is the correspondence sent to Daniel Collins, Assistant General Secretary and Treasurer and Director of Employee Assistance Programs for the UTU. Some of these letters humanize the individual struggles faced by railroad employees during this period. One employee wrote to Mr. Collins to discuss how the use of sniffer dogs sparked PTSD flashbacks to his time as a Prisoner of War in Germany during World War II. The speech by lawyer and recovering alcoholic J. Paul Molloy gave to the Senate in 1984 during subcommittee hearings on substance abuse in the workplace also highlights how a humane approach to these issues might be more successful than harsher disciplinary actions.
Finally, this collection contains a Betamax VHS cassette from the Union Pacific Railroad used as a training tool for Operation: Red Block and its EAP.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5148: Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen Records 5484: Railway Labor Executives' Association Records 5552: Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records 5728: Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records 5139: UTU Records
Alcoholics -- Rehabilitation -- United States; Alcoholism -- Treatment -- United States; Alcoholism.; Collective bargaining.; Drug abuse -- Treatment -- United States; Drug addiction.; Drug addicts -- Rehabilitation -- United States; Employee assistance programs -- United States; Operation Red Block.; Railroad accidents -- United States -- Prevention; Railroad law -- United States; Railroads -- Employees -- Drug testing; Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States; Railroads -- Management -- Employee participation -- United States; Railroads -- Passenger traffic -- Government policy -- United States; Railroads -- United States -- Rule G; Railroads -- United States -- Safety measures; Railroads--United States.; Recovering addicts.; Substance abuse; United States. Federal Railroad Administration -- Rules and practice; Collins, Daniel William, 1921-; Hardin, Fred A.; Molloy, J. Paul.; Paddock, James A.; AFL-CIO.; Amtrak.; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (U.S.).; Burlington Northern.; Conrail.; CSX Transportation.; Norfolk Southern.; Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen.; Railway Labor Executives' Association.; Seaboard System.; South Pacific Railroad.; Southeastern Pennsylvania Transportation Authority (SEPTA).; The Chessie System.; The Milwaukee Road.; The Soo Line Railway.; Union Pacific Railroad Company.; United States. Federal Railroad Administration.; United States. Federal Railroad Administration.; United States. National Transportation Safety Board.; United States. Presidential Railroad Commission.; United Transportation Union.
5713660
- "The Conductor and Brakeman." Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen. Volume 71., 1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "The Conductor and Brakeman." Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen. Volume 72., 1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "The Conductor and Brakeman." Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen. Volume 73., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "The Conductor and Brakeman." Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen. Volume 74., 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "The Conductor and Brakeman." Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen. Volume 75., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Proceedings of the Forty-Sixth Grand Division. Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Scope and Contents
  June 16 1958. Miami Beach, Florida.
- Presidential Railroad Commission Report., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  February 26 1962.
- "The Crew Size Dispute in the Railroad Industry" by Douglas McCabe, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  US Department of Transportation. Federal Railroad Administration.
- "Air and Rail Labor Relations, A Judicial History of the Railway Labor Act" by John W. Gohmann., 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "An Implementation Plan for Recent Legislation." (Concept Paper), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Milwaukee Railroad Restructuring Act of 1979; The Rock Island Transition Act of 1980 as amended by the Rail Deregulation Act of 1980. October 1980.
- Texas Rail System Evaluation: A General Overview of Railroad Safety in Texas, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Texas Transportation Institute. Texas A&M University. August 1977.
- Report to the President by Emergency Board No. 209 and related, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  articles and correspondence re crew consist, Conrail, and railroad labor
- Railroad Safety Improvement Act of 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- United Transportation Union: Unification Agreement and Constitution, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- UTU Constitution, revised November 1, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- UTU brochures and promotional materials, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- UTU promotional materials for Amtrak On-Board Service Employees, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- UTU Correspondence re administrative matters, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- UTU News: volume 16, issues 11, 23, 25; vol. 18, no. 3; vol. 19, no. 5, 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Short Line Agreement between Kyle Railroad Company and the UTU, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Includes "Rule G" By-Pass Agreement
- Collins, Daniel W., UTU Asst. General Secretary: Correspondence to and Report by, in re drug and alcohol testing, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Report by Dan Collins was to the Canadian Parliament o March 24, 1988.
- Miscellaneous personal correspondence, 1973-1987 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- A Proposal for Technical Assistance in Training, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Development and Production of Alcohol Abuse Training for the Illinois Central Gulf Railroad and the Railway Labor Executives Assoc., and 12 month support for RLEA. Submitted to the Federal railroad Administration, July 25 1980.
- Report on Buffalo, New York Alcoholism Conference., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  May 12 1980.
- Progress Report to the New England Task Force on the Feasibility of Employee Assistance Programs on New England Railroads, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  May 13 1981
- Final Report on New England Task Force Seminar on Alcohol Abuse. Philip C. Fedewa, Ph.D., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  May 29 1981.
- Report on the RLEA/EAP "Train-the-Trainer" Pilot Presentations., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  The Railway Labor Executives' Assoc. Employee Assistance Program Workshop.
- The Railway Labor Executives' Association Employee Assistance Program Workshop. Instructor Manual. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- The Railway Labor Executives' Association. Train-the-Trainer Manual for the Employee Assistance Program Workshop. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Iowa Teaching Guide on Alcohol., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Iowa State Commission on Alcohol. 1967.
- Proceedings of 1975 Conference on the Detection, Prevention and Rehabilitation of the Problem Drinking Employee in the Railroad Industry (Box 2, Folder 9)
  New York State School of Industrial and Labor relations. Prepared for federal railroad Administration.
- "A Survey of Alcohol and Drug Abuse Programs in the Railroad Industry", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  November 1976. US Department of Transportation. Federal Railroad Administration.
- "A Proposal to Study the Effectiveness of Railroad Alcohol and Drug Programs", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Submitted by University Research Corporation. December 30 1976.
- "Counseling Alcoholic Clients. Basic Communication Skills. Trainer Manual.", 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism. December 1977
- Training in Communication Skills. Evaluation of Pilot Program for Amtrak and Conrail Counselors, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Submitted by University Research Corporation. November 1978.
- Prevalence, Costs and Handling of Drinking Problems on Seven Railroads., 1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Submitted by University Research Corporation. Final Report. US Department of Transportation. December 1979.
- Problem Drinking Among Railroad Workers: Extent, Impact, and Solutions, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  University Research Corporation (2 copies)
- Project REAP. A Report to the Industry and supporting documents, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- "Preventing Alcohol and Drug Related Accidents on Railroads." T.A. Mannello, J.A. Paddock, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- "A Resource paper on railroad alcohol and drug abase prevention programs." J. A. Paddock, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Folder contains drafts of paper
- Speech by James A. Paddock on Alcohol and Drug Use Prevention in Railroad Employees and on Employee Assistant Programs, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Contains biographic information
- Report on Employee Prevention Programs. James A. Paddock (Box 2, Folder 20)
  undated
- National Conference on Alcohol and Drug Abuse in Railroad Industry, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- National Planning Conference on Drugs and Alcohol Prevention in Railroad Industry - papers, drafts and correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- National Planning Conference on Drugs and Alcohol Prevention in Railroad Industry, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- National Planning Committee on Voluntary Alcohol and Drug Abuse Programs [folder 1 of 2], 1984 (Box 2, Folder 24a)
- National Planning Committee on Voluntary Alcohol and Drug Abuse Programs [folder 2 of 2], 1984 (Box 2, Folder 24b)
- National Planning Committee on the Establishment of Voluntary Alcohol and Drug Use Prevention Programs, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Working Group, National Planning Committee on Voluntary Alcohol and Drug Abuse Programs. Subcommittee on drugs, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Working Group on EAP Counselors, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Draft Standards for Accreditation of Laboratories Engaged in Urine Sample Drug Testing, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  National Institute on Drug Abuse
- Atchison, Topeka and San Francisco Railroad anonymous questionnaire on drug testing, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  by University of Kansas professor
- Clippings on drug and alcohol abuse and the railroad industry [folder 1 of 2], 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 30a)
- Clippings on drug and alcohol abuse and the railroad industry [folder 2 of 2], 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 30b)
- NTSB reports on alcohol and drugs as contributing factors to railroad accidents, 1974-1983 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Transportation Secretary Elizabeth Dole and Dug and Alcohol Testing, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- UTU correspondence re "Rule G" implementation and by-pass agreements, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Statements of J. Paul Molloy before Senate Surface Transportation Subcommittee, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  On voluntary alcohol abuse prevention programs
- Notice of Proposed Rulemaking: Control of Alcohol and Drug Use in Railroad Operations, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Department of Transportation, Federal Railroad Administration. June 5,1984.
- Department of Transportation, Federal Railroad Administration. Control of Alcohol and Drug Use in Railroad Operations, Final Rule., 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Department of Transportation, Federal Railroad Administration. Correction and Amendment of Final Rule; Control of Alcohol and Drug Use in Railroad Operations, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Department of Transportation, Regulations and Programs Regarding Alcohol and Drug Abuse, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- House and Senate Hearings on Alcohol and Drug Abuse in Transportation, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Includes testimony of UTU President Fred Hardin
- Department of Transportation, Federal Railroad Administration. Informal Safety Inquiry; Control of Alcohol and Drug Use in Railroad Operations, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Transportation Employee Safety and Rehabilitation Act of 1987 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Requires drug and alcohol testing of employees
- Testimony of James R. Snyder (RLEA) before the House Subcommittee re alcohol and drug testing, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Department of Transportation, Federal Railroad Administration. Railroad operating rules: random drug testing program. Final Guidelines, Amendments, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- H.R. 4748, "The Railroad Drug Abuse Prevention Act of 1988" and response from labor organizations and carriers (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Lawsuits filed by RLEA against drug and alcohol testing of employees, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Lawsuits filed by RLEA against drug and alcohol testing of employees [folder 1 of 2], 1987 (Box 3, Folder 14a)
- Lawsuits filed by RLEA against drug and alcohol testing of employees [folder 2 of 2], 1987 (Box 3, Folder 14b)
- Lawsuits filed by RLEA against drug and alcohol testing of employees, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Union Pacific Railroad: Employee Assistance Program, Activity Report 1972-1988 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Origin of Operation: Redblock
- Union Pacific Railroad. Operation Red Block, making "Rule G" work, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Betamax video cassette, TRT 16:00.
- Resume of James P. Whalen, EAP counselor for Union Pacific System, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Proposal to Federal Railroad Administration to Implement Operation Red Block, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Operation Red Block, general correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Operation Red Block Promotional Materials (Box 3, Folder 21)
  stickers, flyers, posters, brochures
- Operation Red Block, handouts and posters, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Operation Red Block, training materials (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Agreement between UTU and Union Pacific for Rule G By-Pass and Operation: Red Block programs, 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Agreement between UTU and Green Bay and Western Railroad Company for Rule G By-Pass and Operation: Red Block programs, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Agreement between UTU and Port Terminal Railroad Assoc. and between UTU and Houston Belt and Terminal Railway Co. for Rule G By-Pass and Operation: Red Block programs, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Agreement between UTU and Southern Pacific Transport Company for Rule G By-Pass and Operation: Red Block programs, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Agreement between UTU and Burlington Northern for Rule G By-Pass and Operation: Red Block program, 1982-1986 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Agreement between UTU and Soo Line Railroad Company for Rule G By-Pass and Operation: Red Block programs, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Agreement between UTU and Seaboard System Railroad Company for Rule G By-Pass and Operation: Red Block programs, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Agreement between UTU and Conrail for Rule G By-Pass and Operation: Red Block programs, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Agreement between UTU and CSX Transportation for Rule G By-Pass and Operation: Red Block programs, 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Agreement between UTU and Amtrak for Rule G By-Pass and Operation: Red Block programs, 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- UTU correspondence re carriers unwilling to agree to Operation: Red Block programs, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- UTU correspondence re confidentiality issues in Operation: Red Block program on Union Pacific, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Operation: Red Block, clippings and press materials, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Proposal for case study of Operation: Red Block by Institute for Human Resources, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Operation: Red Block Research Monograph, A case study of peer drug prevention program for railroad operating personnel (draft), 1988 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- "Operation Red Block, Case Study" (draft four), 1988 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- "Operation: Red Block Case Study", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  (3 copies)
- "Using Behavioral Techniques to Improve Safety Program Effectiveness", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  Data from "Operation: Road Block Case Study"
- Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 42)
  orphaned papers found in collection at time of re-foldering